Guide to the Bureau of Applied Social Research records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series I: Project Index
  - David Sills The Volunteers (National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis Study), 1954, (505 pp.: 32 folders and 1 binder Binder- Draft of Sills's book (1955). Folders contain Draft for Sills's book - 3 volumes (1954-1956), National Foundation study in 3 volumes: Sills- Editor (1954- B.A.S.R.), Empty folder (Sills's article or book), Article- Sills, Interview instructions, Interim reports, volunteers interviewed by B.A.S.R., Misc. correspondence, Request for allotment from special funds, Reviews of Sills's book, Memos, Master chapter card, Codebook (mastercopy), Codebooks, Volunteer code - index & instructions, Worksheets, Questionnaires) (Box 38 & 39, Folder *B-0481)
    [This assesses the nature and strength of current (1954) volunteer and public support for the National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, in order to ascertain political support for a future program having an emphasis other than the treatment and control of infantile paralysis. 234 volunteer leaders were interviewed and 459 in a sample of 888 rank-and-f'ile volunteers returned mailed questionnaires. Published in revised form as The Volunteers, Glencoe, IL: The Free Press, 1957. Report: B-0481; B-0481-2; B-0481-5 Book: Sills 1957 (Published dissertation), Articles: Sills 1959, 1961]
  - Lazarsfeld Implementation Commission for Television, 1953, (B-0482-1: 50 pp., B-0482-2: 78 pp., B-0482-3: 76 pp., B-0482-4: 79 pp., B-0482-5: 68 pp., B-0482-6: 68 pp., B-0482-7: 118 pp., B-0482-8: 72 pp., B-0482-9: 65 pp., B-0482-10: 146 pp., B-0482-11: 62 pp.: 16 folders and 1 book Book- background paper for the Implementation Commission on Television by Looell. Nine Empty folders (reports: B-0482-1, B-0482-3 through B-0482-8, and B-0482-10, and B0482-11, with copies supposed to be in Vienna), Background paper (Klapper), Bibliography, Examples of service papers, Proposal & Memos, Conference, Television committee memos, ICTV correspondence) (Box 39, Folder B-0482)
    [B-0482-1 This reformulates the new directions in which communications research should proceed, especially with regard to research on the television media. The report also contains a small sample of significant contributions of past communications research to present (1953) thinking. B-0482-2 Forty adult respondents were interviewed in order to analyze and describe socially prevalent concerns relative to children and television. Such topics as "crime and violence in program content," "seeing adults in conflict" and "what is a good children's program" are discussed. B-0482-3 The report illuminates ways in which interpersonal relations operate to impede or facilitate the effects of mass media and reviews some of the findings of small group research as an aid in the planning of mass media research. B-0482-4 Analyzing articles on television programs and programming appearing during a three-year period in popular and semipopular publications, trade publications and scholarly journals, this report investigates the nature of criticisms of television and attempts to answer "who says what about television and programming?" B-0482-5 In order to provide a broader base for the study of contemporary mass media (particularly television) this report investigates some of the significant elements of the historical discussions which have centered around the problem of art versus entertainment. Ideas of such men as Montaigne, Pascal, and Goethe are discussed. B-0482-6 This paper provides a preliminary analysis of television's present performance, its potentialities and the problems involved in realizing its potentialities in the area of political communication. B-0482-7 The New York State Television Commission was established to study the cost, methods of financing, social and economic consequences of different ways to bring educational television to the public. Part I of this report presents the history of the New York Television Commission based on minutes of meetings, correspondence, and reports; Part II studies and appraises the major assumptions underlying the cornmission's final proposals. B-0482-8 What objectives organizations such as Boy Scouts, National Safety Council and YMCA hope to achieve, as well as problems faced in the use of television are discussed. B-0482-9 This bibliography comprises an annotated list of research projects conducted on television before 1954. Its sources include all available published material. The references are organized into areas of content, audience, and effects. A section concentrating on children and television is also included. B-0482-10 This report studies the organization and operations of seven "public policy councils" or commissions selected by the Implementation Committee on Television to better understand how such groups function. The organizations are also compared and contrasted. B-0482-11 This final report summarizes the work of the Implementation Committee and presents a history of the project. Recommendations are made concerning the organization of a Television Development Center. Reports: B-0482-1 through B-0482-11]
  - Bennington Community Study (Vermont), 1954, (6 folders containing Master codebook, Codebook, Card & records, Content analysis, Questionnaire) (Box 39, Folder B-0483)
  - Fred Ikle and Harry Kincaid Wartime Evacuation of American Cities, 1954, (138 pp.: 5 folders containing Proposals, Final report (two copies), Monograph (Ikle & Kincaid), Contract and one Empty Folder which is listed as having contained a copy of the Report.) (Box 39, Folder B-0484)
    [Deals with social and economic problems of evacuation: billeting, human relations in reception communities, re-employment of evacuees, transportation, administration. Uses material on World War II evacuation in Britain and flood disaster evacuation in the Netherlands. Report: B-0484 Monograph: Ikle & Kincaid 1956]
  - Hanan C. Selvin Patterns of Television Viewing (Pilot Study), 1954, (11 pp.: 2 folders containing Report, Report & correspondence) (Box 40, Folder B-0485)
    [This is an attempt to find patterns, based on program type, of television viewing for households as a whole in New Haven. Report includes suggestions which might prove fruitful in future research. Report: B-0485]
  - Hanan C. Selvin Deviant Behavior and Army Leadership, 1955, (B-0490-1: 185 pp., B-0490-2: 120 pp., 14 folders, 1 Binder, and 1 Unbound chapter; Unbound chapter- IV (Styles of Leadership, book?). Binder- codebook. Other Folders contain Codebooks, Coding instructions, Questionnaire, Meeting notes, Final report outline, Deviant behavior proposal (Selvin & Nasatir), Contract, Report in two parts, Paper- Nonduty Behavior of Army Trainees and one Empty folder whcih may have contained a copy of the leadership book. ) (Box 40, Folder *B-0490)
    [Published as The Effects of Leadership, Hanan C. Selvin, Glencoe, IL: The Free Press, 1960. B-0490-1 Soldiers in 12 training companies were surveyed for frequency of 20 types of leisure activity in order to determine effect of type of company leadership and trainee's age, education and marital status upon such activities. B-0490-2 Appendices, including behavior and leadership questionnaires. Reports: B-0490-1; B-0490-2 Book: Selvin 1960 Dissertation: Selvin 1956]
  - Lipset & Lazarsfeld Propositional Inventory on Political Behavior (Ford Grant), 1953, (Two Empty folders whcih are listed as having contained a Lipset article, and the Hyman book.. ) (Box 40, Folder B-0495)
    [Reports: not available Books: H. Hyman 1959, Lipset 1960 Article: Lipset et al. 1954]
  - Phillip Ennis, and Charles Emery Beverage Story (They Changed to Tea), 1954, (270 pp.: 9 folders containing Codebook- interview guide, Interviews, Codebook draft, Questionnaire, Proposal/correspondence, Financial statements, Preliminary & Final reports) (Box 40, Folder B-0500)
    [This is a study of which kinds of dissatisfaction with previous beverages and which precipitating factors are most common among persons who have recently become regular tea drinkers. 282 interviews. Questionnaire included. Report: B-500]
  - Ringer-Hillel Foundation Jewish Freshmen Study, 1956, (3 Folders containing Questionnaires and Marginals ) (Box 40, Folder B-0504)
  - Rogoff Occupational Mobility, 1953, (1 folder containing Book review of Rogoff book) (Box 40, Folder B-0505)
    [Report: not available Book: Rogoff 1953]
  - Daniel K. Lowenthal Trends in the Licensing of Popular Song Hits, 1953, (89 pp.: 1 folder containing Two copies of report) (Box 40, Folder B-0507)
    [This report presents the results of an investigation of popular song hits licensed by ASCAP and BMI from 1940-53. Section I comprises summary tables showing the proportion of hit songs licensed by these organizations. Section II consists of annual lists of the 30 most popular song titles in each of seven popularity categories. Report: B-0507]
  - Coleman, Katz, & Menzel Medical Innovation (Flow of Scientific Information among Physicians), 1955-1966, (18 folders and 4 Binders 4 Binders (Codebooks, Description data cards, Guide to relational decks). Folders contain Codebook, Memoranda, Correspondence, Pretest questionnaire, Interview sheets, Questionnaire, Interview guide, Proposal & correspondence, Study (Dissertation-Menzel), Articles, Summary & evaluation of pretest, Study summary, Book manuscript (Coleman, Katz, & Menzel), and one Empty folder which was supposed to have contained "Medical Innovation: A Diffusion Study," by Coleman, Katz, & Menzel.) (Box 41, Folder B-0510)
    [Report: B-0510 Book: Coleman, Katz & Menzel 1966 Articles: Menzel & Katz 1955, Coleman et al. 1957, Menzel 1957 (2), Coleman et al. 1958, Menzel et al. 1959, Menzel 1960, Menzel & Katz 1963 Dissertation: Menzel 1959]
  - Threat Study- Senator McCarthy, 1953, (4 folders containing Field work instructions, IBM code, Memo, Questionnaire) (Box 41, Folder F-0510)
  - Lazarsfeld & Thielens The Academic Mind (Teacher Apprehension Study). Includes: Book- Lazarsfeld & Thielens (2 copies), Master codebook, Codebooks, Finished codebook, Codes & related materials, Questionnaires, Apprehension questions- - John W. Mayer (February, 1959- 2 copies), Misc. memos, Memos, Misc. memos from David Riesman, Memo, Individually generated memos on specific topics, Anxiety study- An interim report, Apprehension study- Appendices, Narrative table of contents, Correspondence, Sampling, Some case studies, Indices in teacher study, Key to Classification of colleges, Reseach Instrument & Master codebook, Interviews, Interviewers, Interviewer specifications, Interviews in Apprehension study- Reisman comments & articles, Interviewing- Interim report, List of colleges by respondent ID & list of interviewers, Comments on colleges, Administrations of sample colleges, Profiles of participating colleges, Colleges which refused to participate, Listing of small Catholic universities, College sample by strata, Extra copies of test draft, List of memos, Bibliography, Correspondence with the University of Chicago, Press releases, Misc. pamphlets & reprints, Memos-Thielens, Topic for study, Inventory of some major results (confidential), Federal Personnel security programs- preliminary study (revised), Newspaper clippings, Newspaper & magazine articles, Comments on Communist-Socialist problem in American schools, NBC TV Program, California Teachers Association Journal, Summary proposals, Inventory of material in file, Productivity of scholars, Masters Essay- Hyman, Memos & papers, Individual papers, Notes on Prof. Kinght's paper, Index & non-index rightists by Ruderman, Individual articles, Lecutres, Lazarsfeld funding memo, more Individual articles, Thielens- preliminary report on anxiety, 1954, ( 121 folders) (Box 42, 43, 44, &amp:45, Folder B-0511)
    [An examination of use of qualitative data in The Academic Mind. Report: B-0511 Book: Lazarsfeld & Thielens 1958 Articles: Lazarsfeld & Thielens 1957, Anderson & Hammond 1968 Masters Essay: Hammond 1957, Johnson 1957, Hyman 1958 Dissertations: Goodman 1962, Goldblatt 1964]
  - William McPhee and Rolf Meyersohn Futures for Radio in the TV Era, 1955, (167 pp.: 8 folders containing Inventory, Misc., Memo, Draft of Research proposal, Paper, Suggested analysis, Report- NBC, and one empty folder that contained a study on the -" Futures for Radio," with a copy supposed to be in copy in Vienna.) (Box 45, Folder B-0512)
    [200 interviews were conducted with families owning television and radio sets in a study of network programming planning and problems for radio in the face of television's growth. Possibilities for the long-run future based on radio's basic and unique resources are discussed. Report: B-0512]
  - Conrad Arensberg & Glock Extremist Organizations in Contemporary America, 1954, (263 pp.: 45 folders containing Proposal, Introduction, Research design, Summary, Tentative project, Minutes, Research proposals for Projects I -IV, Misc. correspondence, Administrative recommendations, Comments on drafts, Financial, Personnel, Administrative memos, Freeman letter, Diagrams, AJC proposal, Study objectives, Administration, List of organizations, Counteraction publication (the issue), Proposals for Historical Projects, Pending miscellaneous, Reference, Inventory projects, Memos, Pending- Community studies, Proposals & articles, Research plan, Paper, Aricles- Hofstader, Articles- Lipset, Report, Questionnaire, Articles & clippings, Description & information on right wing & racist organizations, Issues of American Book Publishers- Bulletin) (Box 45 & 46, Folder B-0513)
    [This is a proposal for a program of research to evaluate the degree to which extremist groups or persons on the "right" threaten the traditional personal liberties of American life. Several working papers which discuss such topics as the historical background of reactionary politics, the "pseudo-conservative revolt," the activities of the radical right as a problem for American democracy, the evidence on clusters, syndromes and patterns in social attitudes, and anti-democratic attitudes in America as based on a public opinion poll are also contained in the project file. Report: B-0513 Article: Lipset 1955 (2)]
  - Zetterberg Conference on Morale, 1954, (13 folders containing Proposal, Notes on Washington, Harriman, Chicago Conferences, Notes on NY Academy of Medicine Conference, Memos, Correspondence, Draft of theme statements for the conference, Bibliography, First study of national goals, Transcript of Harriman Conference- Vol. I (parts 1-2), Revised transcript of Harriman Conference ) (Box 46, Folder B-0514)
  - Herbert Hyman and Charles R. Wright Encampment for Citizenship Study, 1956, (326 pp.: 9 folders containing Questionnaire, Codebook, Coding materials, Correspondence & notes, Proposal, Articles, Book and one empty folder which apparently contained material entitled the "Application of Evaluation Methods.") (Box 46, Folder *B-0515)
    [Questionnaires were answered by 1955 and all previous campers for the study of immediate and long-range changes which occurred as a result of the encampment. There is a detailed discussion of methods of analysis used. Published as Applications of Methods of Evaluation, H. H. Hyman, C. R. Wright and T. H. Hopkins, Berkeley: U. of California Press, 1962. Report: B-0515 Books: Hyman, Hopkins, & Wright 1962, Hopkins 1964 Article: Wright & Hyman 1965]
  - James Coleman, Louis Kriesberg, & Arensberg Community Conflicts and Opinion Formation, 1954-1955, (B-0516-1: 63 pp., B-0516-2: 134 pp., B-0516-3: 63 pp.: 5 folders containing Type draft Article- Coleman, Monograph- Coleman, Report, Outline of analysis- Coleman & Kriesberg, and one empty folder with a copy of the Coleman article supposed to be in Vienna.) (Box 47, Folder B-0516)
    [B-0516-1 This is an attempt to build a foundation for community conflict theory drawing on studies of communities under stress, research on social organization, and psychological research. Suggestions for future research are included. B-0516-2 Based on earlier studies of communities under stress, research on social organization and psychological research, this review attempts to clarify recurrent patterns as they are affected by the setting and initiation of controversy, the dynamics of controversy and factors during the course of controversy. Bibliography included. B-0516-3 This is an attempt to construct a theory of the development of community controversies, based on a review of existing studies. Includes a suggested mathematical formalization of the theory. Reports: B-0516-1 through B-0516-3 Book: Coleman 1957]
  - Rolf Meyersohn and William McPhee Alumni Views of Columbia University, 1954, (141 pp.: 6 folders containing Codes, Questionnaire, Pretest materials, Schematic outline of Alumni poll, and one e which supposedly contains a copy of the report in Vienna.) (Box 47, Folder B-0517)
    [This is an exploratory study of the determinants of alumni support of Columbia, based on 2053 questionnaires returned. Report: B-0517]
  - Jaffe Puerto Rican Population of New York City, 1954, (1 folder containing Monograph) (Box 47, Folder B-0518)
    [Report: B-0518 Monograph: Jaffe 1954]
  - Charles Wright Mass Media Effectiveness- Evaluation Methods, 1954, (62 pp., (Shorter version, International Social Science Bulletin, vol. 7 [1955], pp. 417-430.) 3 folders containing Report, Final proposal and one empty folder that supposedly contained an "article in the loan boxes by Nofell.") (Box 47, Folder B-0519)
    [This discusses how to obtain more objective, reliable information on which evaluations of communications programs can be based. It also provides information on how general research procedures are applied to the special problems faced in evaluating mass media effectiveness. Report: B-0519 Article: Wright 1955]
  - Philip H. Ennis and Sheila Spaulding Performing Arts in Suburbia- Pilot Study, 1956, (117 pp.: 10 folders containing Interviews, Questionnaires, Proposals, Memos, Pilot study, and one empty folder which is supposed to have contained a report of which there is supposed to be a a copy in Vienna.) (Box 47, Folder B-0520)
    [ 61 interviews were conducted in the New York area with attenders and non-attenders to study changes in leisure life of the suburbanite which affect his role as consumer of the performing arts. Background review of the literature is included. Report: B-0520]
  - York Lucci, Stein Rokkan, and Eric Meyerhoff A Library Center of Survey Research Data, 1957, (161 pp. One folder containing Report and Proposal) (Box 47, Folder F-0520)
    [This is a study undertaken to determine the need for and the problems of establishing an international library center of survey research materials. It evaluates the potential utilization of such a center, the availability of research material and the adequacy of the available survey data. Recommendations and conclusions are also included.]
  - League of Women Voters League of Womeen Voters Survey, 1954, (10 folders containing Questionnaires & Code, Questionnaires & questionnaire results, Codebook, Correspondence, List of occupied dwellings in the Bronx, Interview instructions, Tentative notes, Summary of interpretation of survey) (Box 47, Folder B-0521)
  - Role of Scholarships in American Undergraduate Education, 1954, (3 folders containing Research proposal, Rejected proposal, Select bibliography) (Box 47, Folder B-0522)
  - McPhee Cases in the Use of Social Research, 1961, (One article containing Article by McPhee ) (Box 47, Folder B-0523)
  - Hans L. Zetterber An American College for Adults, 1956, (95 pp.: 1 folder containing Report (3 copies)) (Box 47, Folder B-0530)
    [What differentiates a college for adults from an extension school and a "college-age" undergraduate school, with particular emphasis placed upon differences in students and teaching personnel. Report: B-0530]
  - American Philosophical Society, 1954, (1 folder containing Code) (Box 47, Folder B-0531)
  - William McPhee Community Controversies- Pilot Project, 1954, (82 pp.: 1 folder containing Report) (Box 47, Folder B-0533)
    [See also B-0516.
    This report contains a proposal for research on community controversies affecting educational freedom. Educational controversies in the New York metropolitan district were investigated, secondary materials examined and informants consulted about episodes in other parts of the country; hypotheses deserving of a high priority of study were worked out. Report: B-0533]
  - Jaffe Methods of Appraisal of Quality of Basic Data for Population Estimates, 1957, (1 folder containing Report (Manual)) (Box 47, Folder B-0534)
    [Article: Jaffe 1957 (1, 2)]
  - Lee Benson & Thomas J. Pressly Political Historiography, 1956, ( 80 pp.: 8 folders containing Memo, Working paper-Benson, Article-Benson, Proposal, Correspondence, and three empty folders apparently containing a copy of the report by Benson in Vienna; and Articles by Stern, Benson, & Turner.) (Box 47, Folder B-0535)
    [This paper examines five interpretations of the causes of the Civil War in order to determine whether they are in fact different interpretations and if so, what the differences are and how they can be resolved objectively. Report: B-0535 Books: Benson 1960, 1961. Article: Benson 1957]
  - Candidates for Womens Home Companion Club Women of the Year Award, 1954-1955, (2 folders containing Correspondence, Report) (Box 47, Folder B-0536)
  - Rowan, Maruyama, Kincaid Importance of Urban Centers (RAND Study), 1956, (8 folders containing Proposal, Correspondence, Interviews, Research memos- Rowan & Kincaid, Code, Rank order of largest 1000 companies in U.S., Report/Article- Rowan & Kincaid and one empty folder which apparently contained a research memo by Rowan & Monoyama with a copy supposed to be in Vienna.) (Box 47, Folder B-0540)
    [Report: B-0540-1; B-0540-2; Monographs: Rowan & Kincaid 1956, Rowan & Maruyama 1956; Articles: Kincaid & Bright 1957 (1, 2)]
  - Frank Bourne & William McPhee Monitor Study, 1956, (189 pp.: 11 folders containing Questionnaires, Master codebook, Background of study, Memos, Codebook, Monitor trendex ratings, Summary of weekend radio report, Daytime Monitor, Monitor- new NBC radio service-pamphlet, and one empty folder which apparently contained a one page reference to a study report (?)) (Box 48, Folder B-0541)
    [In Baltimore, Peoria, Hartford and San Francisco, 2853 phone interviews and 428 interviews in homes were completed among listeners and nonlisteners to "Monitor," a weekend radio service of NBC. "Monitor" was an experiment in programming designed with the growth of television in mind. Questionnaire included. Report: B-0541]
  - Lennard Anatomy of Psychotherapy-Interaction in Therapy, 1955-1957, (31 Folders containing Proposal & Palmore et al. Article, Technicial reports- Lennard (Monograph) & Bernstein, Book manuscript- Lennard & Bernstein, Code, Questionnaire, Application for research grant, Brief information about project, Excerpts from Jung-"Modern Man in Search of a Soul", Excerpts from Ackerman "Trends in Terminal phase of Student Analysis", Summer progress report, Graphs, Excerpts from Philip Slater "Role Differentiation in Small Groups", Student analysis code, Minutes of meeting on student training, Final therapist questionnaire, First draft of Palmore thesis (Dissertation), Confidential draft of study of project by Lennard, Progress report, Articles- Lennard & Hendin, Exploratory analysis, Selection from the "Psychiatric Interview" by Henry Stack Sullivan, Coding exercises, Notes, Study of change via interviews and/or questionnaire, Draft article- Lennard & Hendin, Draft article- Lennard, Appendix A to study, Appendix B to study ) (Box 48, Folder B-0542)